Working in Paterson Project Collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Working in Paterson Project Collection 1993-2002
AFC 1995/028
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
39 boxes 21 linear feet 12,327 items (5,400 manuscript pages, 6,621 graphic materials, 90 original sound recordings, 204 electronic media, and 12 artifacts)
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
The collection consists of manuscripts, sound recordings, photographs, artifacts, publications, and ephemera from an ethnographic field project conducted by the American Folklife Center, Library of Congress, which documented occupational culture in Paterson, New Jersey in 1994. Subjects include the textile industry, industrial architecture, machine shops, labor unions, family owned businesses, dressmaking, and ethnic restaurants. A single manufacturing firm, Watson Machine International, was the focus of an in-depth study. The project focused on the ways in which community life and values are shaped by work and how the theme of work intersects with other themes, namely family, ethnicity, gender, neighborhood, religion, and change over time.
Scope and Content
The Working in Paterson Project Collection consists of manuscript materials, sound recordings, graphic materials, and artifacts collected during the Working in Paterson Project conducted by the American Folklife Center in 1994. The study was part of the federal Urban History Initiative (UHI) program sponsored in Congress by U.S. Senator Frank R. Lautenberg and administered by the National Park Service's Mid-Atlantic Regional Office. The four-month project, conducted between June and September 1994, explored occupational heritage and culture in Paterson, New Jersey, a city that is considered the cradle of the Industrial Revolution in America. The goal of the project was to examine how the idea of work intersects with other themes, such as family, ethnicity, gender, neighborhood, and change over time. The Paterson community yielded several additional themes that reflect both the history of industry in the United States and the specific experience of Patersonians. These themes include the continuity and change of manufacturing over time; the manufacturing process; the textile industry; industrial architecture; the impact of labor unions; diversity in the workplace; the ethnography of Watson Machine International; Paterson's distinctive food tradition, the Hot Texas Wiener; the role of agricultural occupations in urban areas; and work, family, and home.
In addition to Paterson, supplementary documentation was conducted in the following locations in New Jersey: Bloomfield, Clifton, Haledon, Hawthorne, Pequannock, Totowa, West Paterson, and Woodbridge. Documented ethnic groups include: African Americans, Arab Americans, Colombian Americans, Cuban Americans, Dominican Americans, Greek Americans, Hispanic Americans, Honduran Americans, Irish Americans, Italian Americans, Peruvian Americans, Polish Americans, and Puerto Ricans.
AFC Folklife Specialist, David A. Taylor, directed the field research that was carried out by folklorists Tom Carroll (a Paterson native), Robert McCarl, Susan Levitas, and Timothy Lloyd, documentary photographer Martha Cooper, and Taylor himself. The research team interviewed active and retired workers from important local industries, photographed workers and work-related events, and documented other aspects of Paterson's occupational heritage. Under the terms of the cooperative agreement between the National Park Service (NPS) and the American Folklife Center, the AFC developed and administered a study of occupational culture in Paterson, New Jersey, produced a draft report with the findings of the study and recommendations for future research and cultural programming, and provided the NPS with a reference copy of the field data.
The field research resulted in a multi-format collection. The manuscript materials document the project from 1993, when the initial planning began, to 2002, when the project materials were used to create the online presentation, "Working in Paterson: Occupational Heritage in an Urban Setting," http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/wiphtml/pthome.html. The manuscript materials include "Resource Tools," which include databases and tables created by the processing and digitizing staff to summarize information from the fieldworkers' logs, sound recordings, and graphic materials. Also found are various publications, including books, articles, and ephemera that provide background material on Paterson and urban folklife. Documents regarding the planning, administration, and promotion of the project are available in this series with field notes, graphic materials logs, sound recordings logs, and reports and products from the research.
As noted earlier, this series contains two "post-fieldwork" sections. The first includes publications and ephemera the AFC continued to collect after the fieldwork was completed. The second section includes materials generated by the National Digital Library staff at the Library of Congress while creating the online presentation.
This collection contains 90 original sound recordings, both analog and digital audiotapes. The sound recordings are arranged alphabetically by fieldworker's name and then by tape number. The sound recordings contain interviews with residents of Paterson, New Jersey, and the surrounding area, as well as interviews by David Taylor with U.S. Senator Frank R. Lautenberg and Congressman Bill Pascrell. Almost all of the sound recordings have accompanying audio logs. Information on whether or not an audio log exists for a particular sound recording can be found in the database, "WIP Sound Recordings Collection," which is on a zip disk in folder 1, and in hard copy in folder 4.
The Working in Paterson project produced 6,621 graphic materials, which include black-and white negatives, black-and-white photographic prints, color slides, and color photocopies. Black-and-white contact sheets are available to researchers in the Folklife Reading Room. The graphic materials are arranged alphabetically by fieldworker name, then numerically by slide tray or by contact sheet, and then numerically by individual image. While each of the fieldworkers took photographs, documentary photographer Martha Cooper produced the majority of the images in this series. Fieldworkers created logs for the graphic images that are summarized in the database, "WIP Graphic Materials Collection," (available on a zip disk in folder 1).
It should be noted that Martha Cooper's black-and-white image logs only provide information from roll WIP-MC-B001 to roll WIP-MC-B016, but her black-and-white images proceed to WIP-MC-B036. Using her color slides, it was possible to discern the subjects of these unidentified black-and-white images, but there is no way to be positive of the date these photographs were taken. Martha Cooper's color slides WIP-MC-C097-05 through WIP-MCC114-03 are all labeled with a red "X" because the photographer deemed them to not be among the best of the images. They were ultimately added to the collection because of the value of information they contain. Again, these images do not have corresponding logs, but were identified by comparison with logged color slides, and can also be found in the database.
The electronic media in this collection includes one zip disk, 174 CD-ROMs, and 29 3.5-inch high-density diskettes. The zip disk contains the databases for sound recordings and graphic materials and the contents of 38 diskettes of the fieldworkers' logs and field notes. The CD-ROMs contain digital files used in the online presentation. In July 2004, 29 3.5-inch diskettes were found and were added to the collection.
The final series contains 15 artifacts and ephemeral pieces donated by Paterson informants. The artifacts include product samples from work places in Paterson as well as union memorabilia.
Administrative History
The Working in Paterson Project was undertaken in connection with the federal Urban History Initiative (UHI). In accordance with the initiative, three cities in New Jersey--Perth Amboy, Trenton, and Paterson--each received government funds to develop revitalization programs. The National Park Service's Mid-Atlantic Regional Office administered programs in Paterson, including this study of occupational heritage. AFC Folklife Specialist, David A. Taylor, directed the project and conducted fieldwork along with folklorists Tom Carroll, Susan Levitas, Robert McCarl, Timothy Lloyd, and documentary photographer, Martha Cooper. At the time of the Working in Paterson Project, Tom Carroll was Assistant Director for Collections and Research at the Historical Society of Western Pennsylvania in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Susan Levitas was a self-employed folklorist/cultural consultant in the mid-Atlantic region. Robert McCarl was Research Professor in the Department of Anthropology at Boise State University in Boise, Idaho. Timothy Lloyd was Acting Deputy Director of the American Folklife Center. Martha Cooper was a professional photographer in New York City.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Cooper, Martha, photographer.; Lautenberg, Frank R., interviewee.; Pascrell, Bill, interviewee.; Taylor, David Alan, 1951- interviewer.
Organizations
American Folklife Center, collector.; Archive of Folk Culture (Library of Congress); Catholic Church--Customs and practices.; Library of Congress. National Digital Library Program.; United States. National Park Service. Mid-Atlantic Regional Office, collector.; Watson Machine International.
Subjects
African American business enterprises--New Jersey--Paterson.; African Americans--Employment--New Jersey--Paterson.; Arab American business enterprises--New Jersey--Paterson.; Arab Americans--Employment--New Jersey--Paterson.; Architecture, Industrial--New Jersey--Paterson.; Beauty contestants--New Jersey--Paterson.; Colombian American business enterprises--New Jersey--Paterson.; Community life--New Jersey--Paterson.; Ethnic groups--New Jersey--Paterson.; Ethnic restaurants--New Jersey--Paterson.; Family-owned business enterprises--New Jersey--Paterson.; Field recordings--New Jersey--Paterson.; Hispanic American business enterprises--New Jersey--Paterson.; Hispanic Americans--Employment--New Jersey--Paterson.; Irish Americans--Employment--New Jersey--Paterson.; Italian Americans--Employment--New Jersey--Paterson.; Labor unions--New Jersey--Paterson.; Labor--New Jersey--Paterson.; Machine shops--New Jersey--Paterson.; Occupations--New Jersey--Paterson.; Pageants--New Jersey--Paterson.; Polish Americans--Employment--New Jersey--Paterson.; Processions--New Jersey--Paterson.; Textile industry--New Jersey--Paterson.; Textile workers--New Jersey--Paterson.; Women dressmakers--New Jersey--Paterson.
Places
Paterson (N.J.)--Religious life and customs.; Paterson (N.J.)--Social life and customs.
Titles
Working in Paterson: a survey of occupational culture in Paterson, New Jersey, with recommendations for public programming.; Working in Paterson Project, 1993-2002; Working in Paterson, occupational heritage in an urban setting
Form/Genre
Ethnography.; Field notes.; Field recordings.; Interviews.; Manuscripts.; Oral histories.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
Administrative Information
Access
Access to the collection is unrestricted. Upon request, reference copies of the sound recordings and the black-and-white contact sheets are available in the Folklife Reading Room. Duplication of the collection materials may be governed by copyright and other restrictions. Information about ordering audio and photographic reproductions is available on the Library of Congress American Memory website at http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/wiphtml/order.html. A selection of manuscript materials, photographic images, collection is available online as the "Working in Paterson: Setting," through the American Memory web site at http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/wiphtml/pthome.html.
Acquisition
The Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center (AFC), accessioned the Working in Paterson Project Collection, the product of an AFC-sponsored project, in 1995. During the digital conversion process, from 2000 to 2002, manuscript materials and electronic media were also added to the collection. Initial processing of the collection was done by Robin Fanslow. Christa Maher curated the online presentation of the collection from November 2000 to May 2002. Rosemary Graham arranged and processed the collection and created the initial version of the collection in September 2002. In July 2004, Sarah Bradley Leighton and Stephanie Schmitz resolved outstanding issues with the sound recordings series and added additional materials that were found after the original processing had been completed. All modifications are reflected in this updated version of the collection guide and its appendices.
Related Materials
A selected version of the same collection is also available at the Paterson Free Public Library in Paterson, New Jersey.
Collection Concordance by Format
Note: Sound recordings originally housed in boxes are stored in a separate location.
Manuscript Materials
143 folders AFC Boxes 1-9
Sound Recordings
39 60-min. audiocassettes (field originals) Boxes 10-12
2 90-min. audiocassettes (field originals) Boxes 10-12
49 digital audio tapes (field originals) Boxes 13-14
51 7-inch reel-to-reel tapes (preservation copies) N/A
Graphic Images
2,697 black-and-white negatives AFC Box 15
3,831 color slides AFC Boxes 16-30, 38
4 8x10 black-and-white photographic prints AFC Box 38
11 8x10 color photocopies AFC Box 38
78 black-and-white contact sheets (reference) AFC Reading Room Binders 1-2
Electronic Media
1 zip disk AFC Box 1, Folder 1
174 CD-ROMS AFC Boxes 31-37
29 3.5-inch high density diskettes AFC Box 38
Artifacts
15 artifacts and ephemera AFC Box 39
http://lccn.loc.gov/2004695193
Container List
- Series I: Manuscript Materials
  - (Box 1)
    - Administrative Files
      - Collection Guide (Folder 1)
        Hard copy of collection guide and zip disk containing the following:
        Graphic Materials database. Fields include: ID number, frame, format, photographer, title, created/published, event, people in photo, location, notes, and repository.
        Sound Recordings database. Fields include: audio number, audio log, informant, date, location, event, subject, format/quantity, and length.
        Contents of Working in Paterson Project Collection diskettes: fieldworkers notes and logs. (See Series IV: Electronic Media)
      - Collection Guide (Folder 2)
        For the Working in Paterson Project Collection housed at the Paterson Public Library in Paterson, New Jersey.
    - Reference Tools
      - Working in Paterson Fieldwork Calendar (Folder 3)
        Calendar for June-September 1994 that lists where the fieldworkers were during the project. 9 pages.
      - Sound Recordings database (Folder 4)
        Hard copy. Fields include: audio number, audio log, informant, date, location, event, subject, format/quantity, and length. 23 pages.
      - Places/People/Events photographed by Martha Cooper (Folder 5)
        Table of places, people, dates, and events photographed by Martha Cooper during the Working in Paterson project. 2 pages.
      - Events in Black and White Photos (Folder 6)
        Table of the events depicted in black and white photographs. Fields include: event, date created, call number, fieldworkers, notes, location. 8 pages.
      - Working in Paterson field notes summary (Folder 7)
        Table of information from field notes; fields include: item, date, location, informant/event, fieldworker, and co-worker. 11 pages.
    - Preliminaries
      - Cooperative Agreement (Folder 8)
        Agreement between American Folklife Center and National Park Service. Draft of agreement, signed final agreement with related correspondence. 50 pages.
    - Planning
      - Background Ideas (Folder 9)
        Memos, notes, budget draft. 17 pages.
      - CHAPMAN, Lloyd (Folder 10)
        (National Park Service contact) Correspondence and planning documentation. 19 pages.
      - Correspondence, National Park Service (Folder 11)
        34 pages
      - Correspondence, TAYLOR, David (Folder 12)
        (Project director). 15 pages.
      - Fieldwork Schedule (Folder 13)
        Outline and two copies of memorandum. 5 pages.
      - Job Announcement (Folder 14)
        Copy of public announcement for researchers. 2 pages.
      - Paterson Contacts (Folder 15)
        Business cards, correspondence, list of names, receipt. 6 pages.
      - Project Applicants (Folder 16)
        Applications, cover letters, resumes, correspondence from applicants selected to work on the project. 20 pages.
    - Background Information
      - Boarding Houses and Residential Health Facilities (Folder 17)
        Directory of facilities in Paterson, a possible setting for project research. 24 pages.
      - H.R. 3498/1104 (U.S. Representative Herbert Klein) (Great Falls Redevelopment/Preservation) (Folder 18)
        Data sheet from Congressional Yellow Book, clipping. 2 pages.
      - LAUTENBERG, Frank R. (Folder 19)
        U.S. Senator (D-NJ). Correspondence, press releases, personal biographical data sheet, consent form, two visitor passes to Senate chamber, and one 8 x 10 black- and-white photo. 29 pages.
      - Lowell National Historic Park (Folder 20)
        Park handbook, map, press releases, museum and festival brochures that provide examples of the city's industrial heritage. 20 pages.
      - N.J. Urban History Initiative (P.L. 102-154) (Folder 21)
        11 pages.
      - The Paterson Great Falls/S.U.M. National Historic Landmark District Condition Assessment Project Summary Report. (Folder 22)
        8 pages.
      - Paterson Urban History Initiative Advisory Committee (Folder 23)
        Advisory committee meeting outlines and notes, project status report, grant program notes. 22 pages.
    - Project Personnel
      - CARROLL, Tom (Folder 24)
        Fieldworker project proposals, contract, invoices, and progress reports, related correspondence, related paperwork from LC travel office. 79 pages.
      - COOPER, Martha (Folder 25)
        Fieldworker correspondence, contract, LC purchase orders, LC purchase requisitions, notes. 33 pages.
      - Fieldworkers (Folder 26)
        Memo, notes. 3 pages.
      - Guide for Project Fieldworkers (Folder 27)
        "Notes on Archiving and Media Documentation: A Guide for Project Fieldworkers Prepared in Connection with the Project 'Working in Paterson'"(2 copies). 68 pages.
      - LEVITAS, Susan (Folder 28)
        Fieldworker correspondence, contract, LC travel requisitions, notes. 33 pages.
  - (Box 2)
      - McCARL, Robert (Folder 29)
        Fieldworker correspondence, contract, invoices, notes. 31 pages.
      - SMITH, Lynda (Folder 30)
        Fieldwork assistant contract and invoice. 4 pages.
      - TORRADO, Carlos (Folder 31)
        Fieldwork assistant contract and cancellation. 3 pages.
    - Equipment and Expenses
      - Equipment (Folder 32)
        List of documentation equipment used during field survey. 16 pages.
      - Expenses (Folder 33)
        Preliminary accounting of expenses. Invoices, purchase orders and miscellaneous documents. 126 pages.
    - Publicity and Public Relations
      - Business Cards (Folder 34)
        Business cards for the Working in Paterson fieldworkers.
      - Certificates of Appreciation (Folder 35)
        Copies of certificates sent to informants and others who assisted with the project. 8 blank certificates.
      - Correspondence, Informants (Folder 36)
        Letters sent to informants along with copies of Folklife Center News featuring articles about the Working in Paterson Project. 5 pages.
      - Folklife Center News (Summer 1994), Vol. XVI, No. 3 (Folder 37)
        "American Folklife Center Documents Occupational Culture in Paterson, New Jersey," by David Taylor. 3 copies.
      - Folklife Center News (Spring 1995), Vol. XVII, No. 2 (Folder 38)
        "Narratives of Work: Stories Told by Retired Workers and Their Children," by David Taylor, and "Paterson's Hot Texas Wiener Tradition," by Timothy Lloyd. 3 copies.
      - Folklife Center News (Summer 1995), Vol. XVII, No. 3 (Folder 39)
        "African American Family Business in Paterson, New Jersey," by Susan Levitas. 3 copies.
      - Hot Texas Wiener Articles: (Folder 40)
        Two articles that mention American Folklife Center's Working in Paterson project. 4 pages.
        "Hot Texas Wiener entrepreneurs are on a roll," The Record, July 9, 1995. (2 copies)
        "Secret still in the sauce," The Record, July 16, 1995.
      - Letter of Appreciation to Informants (Folder 41)
        Post-project correspondence with informants. Letters of thanks, letters accompanying Folklife Center News article. 26 pages.
      - Library of Congress News press release (Folder 42)
        "American Folklife Center Documents Occupational Culture in Paterson, N.J." English and Spanish copies. 3 pages.
      - Mailing List (Folder 43)
        Informants' addresses. 5 pages.
      - Project Handout (Folder 44)
        English and Spanish. 3 pages.
    - Publications
      - Botto House/American Labor Museum (Folder 45)
        6 pages, 3 pamphlets, 3 booklets (68 pages each)
      - Dominican Parade (Folder 46)
        Flyer
      - Dyers Local 1733 (Folder 47)
        COSTA, Marianne (informant). Unpublished story of her memories and experiences of Dyers Local 1733, Amalgamated Clothing Textile Workers Union of America. 8 pages.
      - Famous Patersonians (Folder 48)
        "Fifty Famous Patersonians Across 200 Years" from the Great Falls Visitor Center. 1 page.
      - Hot Texas Wieners (Folder 49)
        "Geography Quiz: Where's the Texas in the Texas Wiener?," New York Times, Sunday, January 12, 1997. 1 page.
      - "The Limited Fame of Sam Patch" (Folder 50)
        By Kathleen M. Kavanaugh. New York Folklore Quarterly, Volume XXVIII, Number 2, June 1972: Study of a man who jumped into waterfalls. William Carlos Williams dedicated several pages of his poem Paterson to Sam. 17 pages.
      - The Mill Street Forward (Folder 51a)
        [See Box 39]
        June 1987, Volume 1, Number 1. 12 pages.
      - The Mill Street Forward (Folder 51b)
        Spring/Summer 1990, Volume 1, Number 5. 12 pages.
      - New Jersey Urban History Initiative Newsletter (Folder 52)
        The View From the Falls, Spring 1995. (2 copies) 8 pages.
      - Paterson Community Information (2 folders) (Folder 53-54)
        Miscellaneous Paterson information. 212 pages.
  - (Box 3)
      - Paterson Economic Development Corporation (Folder 55)
        Housed in promotional folder. Includes: Paterson profile, retail center and notable area resources, business mix and prominent employers, business resources, transportation, Paterson Economic Development Corporation board of directors. 6 pages.
      - Paterson Museum Photos (Folder 56)
        Two black-and-white 8 x 10 photographs depicting scenes inside textile mills.
      - Picture Postcards (Folder 57-65)
        Postcards depicting various sites in and around Paterson, N.J. 9 cards.
      - San Rocco Festival (Folder 66)
        Program from the "Comitato Festa Patronale San Rocco." 1 pages.
      - STETIN, Sol (2 folders) (Folder 67-68)
        Background information about Stetin, a WIP informant who was a textile-union activist. 176 pages.
      - Textile Industry (Folder 69)
        General information on northern New Jersey textiles. 2 pages.